[Music] Thank you thank you thank you
very much for this
warm
welcome for those who don't know me
my name is Mario Mario Guerra and I am
dedicated to psychology psychology and
human development and during my
work over the years as a
psychotherapist author and communicator on
issues of Mental Health and
human development I have seen that one of the
most important issues in
our lives is the issue of attachment but
attachment needs
public relations and that is why I am here in
defense of attachment because I have heard
hear people tell me in
different workshops at conferences
Mario How do I detach myself How do I get
rid of these attachments that
torment me and I tell them that we can't
because What is attachment attachment
tells us that it is a deep emotional bond
that initially occurs between a
boy a little girl and their
primary caregivers usually their father and
mother it is an innate need that
we have to seek love and protection from
those people who are supposed to take
care of us who are supposed to
love us deeply more than
Anything else there is in life
then we tend to seek out that closeness
this proximity to receive exactly
that love and care. But then this is
this bad public relationship that
attachment suddenly has when we say that we have to
take it away from us. I say how do we
take away that basic need? We cannot
survive if we are not cared for if we
are not loved by other people who are
going to help us move through life
while we learn to be independent and
self-sufficient.
So the issue with attachment is not whether we
have it or not, the question is,
what is my way of attaching? What is my
attachment style? And that is what
attachment theory tells us about. Attachment theory
tells us there are four ways that
people learn to attach to
their loved ones, depending a lot on
how they were raised. How they were
raised during childhood. What is
attachment style? It is the way that a
boy or a little girl responds to the
way they are loved and cared for by their
parents. Whether the parents gave
consistent support, whether they gave
unconditional love, whether they were attentive to
the needs of the boy or the
little girl.  that child is going to learn that
love does not hurt That he can trust those
people who are taking care of him but
above all that he can trust that he
is a person worthy of being loved the
problem comes when the way of creating
gave us answers that are like
strategies to survive in an
environment that is little less than kind and this
can come in several ways because
attachment can be secure attachment
anxious attachment avoidant attachment or
disorganized attachment If I had to give a
very concrete example and very one that we
could all get closer to, let's imagine
a child's first day of school, a
little girl the first time she goes to
school if we stand outside
a kindergarten of some school to
see the reactions we will see
that there are children who are arriving very
happy with their backpack in their hand holding their
mom's hand holding their dad's hand they are
talking they are excited because it is their
first day of school they arrive at the door they
look with curiosity and soon the
teacher is there to receive them and the child
says to the mother yes go go with the teacher
here you will be fine the child trusts
because he says my mother has never
betrayed if he's telling me that I'm going
to be okay, I'm going to be okay he
comes in perfect he says goodbye to mom and
mom says on the way out I'll be back for you
and that boy girl knows that she's going to come back
for him he has no doubt that's why she's
going to dedicate that day of school to
learning to play, to be friends because he's not going to
be attentive all the time whether I'll come back
or not They're going to come back for me
when mom comes back for him dad comes back
for him he greets him with a hug an
excited hug that says you arrived
I love you and we go home and the next day we
return same scenario anxious attachment we
see a boy little girl hugging
her father's leg her mother who
says no no don't leave me No I don't want to
be here I'm very scared it's not that
you have to go to school It's that I don't want to go do
n't leave me are you going to come
with me no no I'm not going to no it's that I want
you to stay with me and at that moment well that
boy that girl who is grabbing feet and
hands to the school door so as not to
enter Well almost the father or the mother
says But how not if you go inside the
teacher pulls him towards  inside and the child
says This is a very stormy thing
to end here they are abandoning me in this
place and that boy is going to cry that girl is going
to cry in there he is going to be
distressed my mother is going to come back eh she is
going to grab onto the teacher she is not going to want to
play with the children and and when the
exit comes and his mother is going to arrive because she will
arrive well she is going to hug her as if it
were a miracle that she had arrived and she
says now yes I am never going to let you go again
and the next day the same thing and the
same thing and the same thing that boy that
anxious girl is going to be a person who
being an adult is going to develop a
great need for reassurance from
others it is the adult who says I sent you a
message why didn't you answer me
but it's because I was working You do
n't see how distressed I get Because of this I
thought something had happened to you I thought they
had killed you I thought they had
kidnapped you I thought you didn't love me anymore I
thought you were with someone else it is going to
be the jealous adult the
manipulative adult the adult who is
always suspecting that something more is going on the one who
is having the certainty that
they are going to be abandoned because it is not  worthy of
being loved Why Because they gave him an
inconsistent belief they didn't attend to
his needs well And suddenly that made him
unable to trust what he prioritizes with
anxious attachment or distrust
we returned to the same scenario now a
boy a girl who arrives on the first day of
school enters the school doesn't even
turn to look at his mother doesn't say goodbye he
enters as if nothing happened the mother says Well
then he came in very confident one sees him as
a very secure child he enters he doesn't interact he
prefers not to play he prefers not to
interact with the teacher he goes alone to a
corner he may seem like that little
intellectual child who is reading something very
concentrated but always alone
because he has lost hope why
Because at home that little child his
needs were not heard they
were not satisfied he is the child they
told him Oh don't bother Look at the tablet
start playing what do you want now again It's that I
want to go to the bathroom well Go to the bathroom
don't bother me don't you see that I'm busy he
is the child they told him No no no
crying eh you want to cry I'm going to give you
reasons to cry so that you cry
hard Don't you see that I am very busy
What  you're missing see what you're missing you have a
home you have food you have toys you have
friends what are you missing Well that
child can't say one very
important thing I miss you You are the one I
miss you are the one who is not there
for me you are the one who doesn't even see my
eyes because you have your
eyes on your cell phone all the time and then it seems
that what is there is more important
than me And then that child learns not to
bond he has already lost hope because it
seems he is a child his world is cold and gray
wherever I turn who nobody is going to pay
attention to me nobody is going to listen to me and it is
less painful to be the one who rejects than to
approach to ask for something and be
rejected by another the one who can't even
give me your look and your
attention and finally perhaps The worst of
all we return to the scene of the
little boy entering school that
little boy who says to his father or his
mother don't leave me please because I am
dying of anguish don't
abandon me in this school and and the father is that
you have to go to school I'm
sorry but you have to go in and
suddenly the child says you know what
Then I don't want to see you again Never
never in my  life I want to see you again
if you leave me I'm going to hate you for the
rest of my life that child who was
begging for love Suddenly rejects him and
says go away I never want to see you again
because he is a child who suffered
abuse he suffered mistreatment it is a
disorganized attachment it is a very confusing attachment
because that is precisely how he is going to
become the adult that you will not be
able to predict an adult who when he
goes to work eh Suddenly he has
aggressive violent
explosive reactions the one you say why did he get angry
if we didn't tell him anything because he is already
used to responding So when he
feels that there is danger that there is a threat he
reacts immediately with fear and that
fear leads to aggression so in
secure attachment what is fostered
is precisely trust in
anxious attachment it is anguish in
avoidant attachment it is hopelessness and in
disorganized attachment it is fear the fear
that if I ask for something they are going to punish me
if I say that I need something they are going to
judge me and it is a boy a girl who lives
with a big  fear but also with a
great need to be loved like all of
us that is why attachment lacks
public relations it is not about not
having it it is about how we are going to
have it how we are going to develop it and one
sometimes I should say son of daddy
mom better they had left me some
property in the Caribbean No no no this
style of attachment that suddenly costs me
so much work and that and it is going to mark my
relationships not only with my partner it is going to
mark my work relationships it is going to
mark my relationships with friends and it is
going to mark the relationship with myself
because attachment is about how I learned
to expect love from others what I believe
is my place in front of others and how I
think love and care are does it
hurt or not it hurts do I trust or I don't trust that is what it is about
that is so fundamental
in our lives all of us
develop attachment The question is what
is my style how am I doing and the
big question that we will be answering can it be
changed or is this already a
condemnation That is the question that everyone
is surely asking because because
from here everything can be seen and I can see in
some of you as I was
telling this some  tear some
sigh he will be feeling Because
many of you identify
with things that you have surely seen with
children at the entrance of a
school but you identified with something that I have
spoken about here because this is
the human experience it is
human nature this is attachment the attachment lives
beyond the theory in each one of
us Hello I am FZ the truth is that
I feel an honor to be here with you I have
known you for many years and um I have
a question with a face of three what generates the
attachment mom or dad and from
what age does it begin to
reflect Thank you very much Fernanda Thank you
for your question eh the attachment is formed
from the moment we are born the attachment is going to be
formed from our
primary caregivers who are normally dad and
mom and I say normally because
Unfortunately sometimes it happens that one is not
present or both are not present
sometimes it happens that a mother dies at the
birth of a child for some reason and that And the thing is not that
that child is not going to
develop attachment he will develop it
but he will develop it with other
important people in his life in fact it
is true that parents are the
main eh founders of attachment in
us but also all those
people with whom we are going to live
intensively they can be grandparents
For example if we are taking care of
grandparents they can be older siblings
sometimes they can even be uncles all
the people who are
around us but of course it is assumed that we are
mainly going to be linked
to the figure of our parents but
very fundamentally with what we
know as the main dyad which is
the mother son or daughter relationship because it is
the first it is the most basic the
most elementary from the
mother's womb we already come in some way
experiencing the emotions of our
mother and at birth she will most likely
be the first person who is going to
receive us in her arms and from her we are going to
receive the first sources of this
way of attaching ourselves that sometimes there are
people there are mothers who are assumed that
because they are a mother they would have to love
their children unconditionally but there are
mothers who cannot do it for some
reason what happens when that happens if that
mother who rejects is a cold
distant inexpressive mother that child is going to
develop an avoidant attachment style he is going
to say I don't have  hope this
lady mom doesn't answer me no matter what
I do she doesn't look at me she doesn't pay attention to me she does
n't take care of me she doesn't pamper me I'm not even going to
ask for that because I already know that I'm not going to have it that's why
I was talking about
hopelessness it's terrible to
suddenly hear mothers angry with their children
telling them as if it were an insult
you're just like your father now you don't know
how to receive it no thank you or who no
how do I respond to that or to them telling me the
same you're just like your mother you're
crazy like your mother Well at that
moment I realize those messages are going to
condition the development of the
most terrible attachment style that someone can
have which is the disorganized attachment that's why I
said that child is going to react
first looking for love but as soon as he
feels that he isn't given it and no one is going to be
able to give it to him because as he imagines it doesn't
exist then he is going to react with
violence with rejection he is the one who is going to
reject before being rejected the one who is going to
blow up a relationship that could have been
good because he is certain that he is going to
be hurt he lives in
eternal fear  Imagine walking into a house
like that with a mother who refuses to walk in the
house and not knowing if the next step I'm
going to take is going to cause an explosion, it
's like walking through a minefield, I
don't know if it's going to appear or not, you
have to be able to predict
the people you live with in some
way, I don't understand that maybe one
day you woke up feeling sick and maybe you don't
talk to me for some reason And he says, Okay,
well, I understand that you've been stressed
but not the next minute, I mean,
how are you going to respond I'm playing and
suddenly he says, Oh, how nice that you're
playing and suddenly I continue playing and he says, shut
up You're not letting me
concentrate, so I say, Okay
then it's wrong, the one who's wrong is
me, suddenly they tell me that I start
drawing and suddenly they complain to me
how many sheets of paper I waste and that if we don't have
money to pay for so many sheets of paper
that I should be more aware of the
expenses of the house suddenly they tell me that I have to
eat and finish what's on my plate
and when I say that I want more because
everything is very delicious they tell me that this is not an Inn
that  I since I have to conform
with what they give me that I should not be greedy
that besides my brothers also have to
eat So I don't know how they are going to
respond, are they going to take care of me, they are not going to
take care of me, they are going to smile, they are not going to smile and
that makes us develop a
very strange defense mechanism to be as
unpredictable as the adults who
created us later it can
clearly change there are things that we can do we
are not condemned but we can all
aspire to have a better attachment style
to relate in a different way I have
always said that it is as important to
love as to know how to love and knowing how to love is knowing how to
transmit the love that is felt in a way that the other can understand that that is love but also the way to receive love because many times especially for example when we have anxious attachment we are already with distrust ahead and living in
constant fear in
constant danger worse than if
ghosts really existed is living in that
anguish that no child
or
adult would ever have to live with we would never
have to live in fear love does
not
scare Love
receives Hello My name is Luis Mendiola
I am lucky to be here and I
question is why does that toxic attachment exist?
Thank you Luis. Thank you for your
question and thank you for being here
too.
Look, attachment is not toxic, what is
toxic is the way some children
are treated. What is toxic is that which makes you sick, that which
intoxicates, that which
is not proper to the organism that
has it but when it consumes it, when it
acquires it, it becomes sick and that is it and it is fortunate and
unfortunate
because it is not part of us,
our nature is
inherently loving, our nature is
naturally benevolent when something
intoxicates us or we get hives or or or we
want to vomit or we get sick. Well,
but we are not the sick ones, we
are sick because of what was
given to us that was not healthy and wholesome. A
small child cannot choose. How are
their parents going to be? And here is something very
important that we have to understand.
Our parents and other
significant figures in our lives
cannot teach us. How is the world? They
transmit to us how they see the world. They
transmit to us their vision of the world, but a
small child cannot make this
distinction yet and small children
say, my parents teach me that love
is like this, that love hurts. So that
must  be love but don't
think about it I would love it if a
little boy could say okay that's what
you say mom that's what you say
dad that's how you see things but
I don't agree and I can't
say it because how come you won't
agree if I'm your father if I'm your
mother the famous one because I say so and
then in that because I say so Well
then it's all over if this
is the law Well then we have to obey
the law because here it seems that
my parents sometimes constitute themselves as
judges juries prosecutors and executioners and I
turn around and say and my defense attorney No I don't
have someone to defend me here well
no Because a little boy does
n't have that capacity yet But
fortunately we can get out of those bonds that we
could call toxic, those
toxic dynamics that exist
when we become
adults we begin to grow and we
begin to question things or even
when another person that's why
a concept is so important
here which is emotional co-regulation
is the ability to regulate
our emotions through
experiences with other people who are
capable  of welcoming us sometimes in a
small child a school teacher a
classmate the mother of a little friend can
give a word of comfort a word
of acceptance a word of love that has
never been received from his own father his
own mother And suddenly that
discovery that
epiphany makes you discover they told me I
'm smart they
told me I'm
handsome they told me I'm intelligent and and it does
n't look like what they've told me that
I'm an idiot that how is it possible that I don't
know How much is 2 + do or if the ha
has the accent on tree or not what's wrong with my
head suddenly someone tells me
very well You're doing very well
and that discovery if it comes at the
right time at the right moment is
the antidote against that toxicity because it
is the type of messages that we are going to
save and we are going to contrast
later over time to be able to say
Okay My parents said This I keep
what was good for me and what was
n't I won't let go because I keep
those other messages from friends
teachers mentors of of from mothers of
other children when that time they
told me that it was not my fault that I
was just a  child and that I was not
responsible for my
parents' emotions when they tell me at the
right moment a world of possibilities opens up to me
the world becomes another and
I begin to see that those who give me these
instructions these internal scripts are
people who also write those
scripts based on their own scripts
the parents  They are like a reflection of the
inner self if you went to the bathroom right now
and looked in the mirror because I don't
know if you want to comb your hair or if
some dirt got in your eye you go to the
mirror and you look in the mirror and you're going to see
your reflection and it's fine but you would have to
understand something that reflection is not you it is
the reflection that the mirror
returns to you but if you go to the bathroom and that
mirror is broken yes And then you go
into the bathroom and the mirror is but
broken really broken Eh like broken into pieces
but there it is on the wall still no
way you will get to the bathroom and say Ah I'm already
broken don't you know that the mirror is the one that
is broken and if it is giving back a
distorted reflection it is because the
problem is with the mirror you are not broken
well that happens sometimes in these
relationships that make us sick they are
broken mirrors that give back a reflection not of
what we are but of how they see us
how they see us because they also come from
their own broken childhoods So we
have to recognize No, that one in the
broken mirror is not me That is a reflection that the
mirror gives back to me and that reflection
can be very faithful to what  that I am or can
be as distorted as in these
fairs of the houses of mirrors where I
see bigger, smaller, fatter,
thinner but finally that is not me and
sometimes it makes us laugh with those reflections no
but it does not make a child laugh when he
returns a reflection and what he sees is a
monster that they were told it was for having
spilled the milk for not having
learned the lesson as they were told they
had to learn it but there is always
hope. Hello, how are you Mario, I am
Evelin Salazar. It is said that throughout
our lives we choose people who
remind us of our parents, our
caregivers. Do you believe that this is true and
if so, do you consider it healthy and from
your perspective and your experience? Do you believe
that we can break these patterns?
Thank you Evely, thank you for
asking? Yes, it is correct, those
patterns are repeated and look, I am going to answer the
question a little bit from back to
front. Is it healthy for this to happen to us? Yes, the
attachment style of our parents, the one they
passed on to us? Is it healthy? Of
course it is. Yes, my parents were
consistent, loving, attentive, bonded
to me, of course I want to repeat
those patterns, in fact I am going to  to repeat
but let's think about the
unfortunate examples that are the ones that
come to mind frequently and I
really like to use the example of the
cactus mother and it is the following imagine
that there is a boy a girl little girl who is
in a room where there is nothing and no
one else suddenly on a table there is
a cactus and you know what
cacti look like they don't have a longer arm and a
shorter one and they are full of thorns
well to that little boy girl they say
look that's your mother
the boy
thinks yes but he doesn't see anyone else there is no
one else and there is a need in that
boy that girl What is the need to
attach to bond is she not going to say oh
no don't bring me a
real mother I don't want her No yes when he sees that
no one else arrives that child is going to say
Well if it's my mother then I'm going to
approach her but there is a danger
you already sense it first that cactus is
not going to move to approach that
boy that girl that boy that girl has to
approach the cactus because the cactus
does not respond the cactus does not move does not
move its arms to hug  Thank
God for the thorns but
the thing is that child is not going to
give up on that idea of that need to
bond And then he's going to approach the
cactus but the first approach is going to
hurt him and he's going to move away a little but
that's not going to make him give up on the
need for acceptance love and
affection So that boy that girl is going to
learn one thing How to approach the
cactus and be close to it in a way that it
hurts me as little as possible But also
the thorns that do, do, do, do, do,
stick in me and cause pain I'm going to
be like the pain doesn't matter so much And
then that child is going to learn to
hug the cactus he's going to learn to sleep
with the cactus But he's going to be feeling
pain permanently then he's going to
grow up and they're going to tell him you've grown up go out into the
world go out into the world and relate what do you
think he's going to look for people cactus
Why is it absurd if the cactus
was hurting him Yes because that's how I
learned what love is Remember the
attachment style is formed in response to
what the other gives me and I already learned and
I have a mastery in enduring pain,
enduring coldness and even in
bonding with kind of green people and
then I go out into the world and I'm going to
find all kinds of people in the world
I'm going to find
loving, caring, warm people who are going to
open their arms to me and say Come
and I'm going to say no and and you V Why not why not
If I want to give you love
no no you don't give love Let's see, let's see Touch me no no no it
hurts no this This isn't love
but no no who knows what it will be you
want to cheat on me This isn't love then I'm
going to have to look for cactus people
people who hurt not because I like to
suffer but because in my
relationship script in my mental map in my
attachment style love is
conditioned by pain it is
conditioned by lack of response and it
is conditioned by coldness and I'm not
going to have any other type of relationships
until I learn that that is not
love and that is the first step love doesn't
have to hurt like I say Love doesn't
have to scare you but until I
learn that I'm going to keep looking for
cactus people in my  life then yes I
think that is fortunate When we have
a secure attachment style when we can
trust and look and and with the
secure attachment style do not imagine that a
secure attachment person is like
saying Well if you want to go go away
I don't have any problem I'm not going to
miss you No a secure attachment person
suffers when a person dies suffers in
an emotional breakup asks themselves many
questions just like the rest of us but there
is a difference with secure attachment
you know that this This loss this breakup is
not what is going to finish you off you know
that you can first lean on other
people you can lean on family You
can lean on friends you can
lean on yourself too because you know
that you are going to get through whatever is
put in front of you one of my
favorite authors Carlos Castaneda said in one
of his books the basic difference between
a Warrior and an ordinary person
is that the ordinary person sees everything that
happens to them as a blessing or a
curse and the warrior sees everything that
happens to them as a challenge the
secure attachment person sees life's setbacks
as challenges that are there to be
overcome no  to learn to live with
them he sees the cactus as a temporary source of
life when there is no other but as
soon as he reaches society and reaches the
community he thanks the cactus for what it
gave him he thanks his
survival mechanism for what it could have
given him that's why he learned to drink from the cactus
but he doesn't go out to look for people cactus
because this challenge is overcome my
childhood is over childhood is not
a curse when as adults we can
rewrite the scripts of our life and
rewrite the scripts of our
history and remember something our
brain has evolved not so much to
make us happy but to
survive when it has the
means of security and trust is
when our brain our mind
can think well now what am I going to
learn Now yes who is going to be my
friend but when you have lived in a
survival environment you no longer
worry about happiness then
our brain is in
survival mode and then it will prefer
the known path it will prefer the
cactus because that one didn't let me die I know it
hurts but but but it is what is known
so I will tend to repeat these
patterns only because they are the
known paths that once
worked for me let's see this example can
help and right now  I'm going specifically to
what can be done in this case, let's
think that you are going on an adventure
through the jungle through the countryside through the
forest it's the same a wooded place
where there are rivers where there are mountains you reach
the edge of a river you have to
cross it it's a very fast and very
deep river no you can't cross it there
because the current takes it away
but suddenly in the distance you see a
raft and they say there it is the raft it doesn't belong to
anyone in fact there is one that says whoever
wants to use it to get to the other side
perfect what helps me at that moment
to cross is a raft I get to the other side
of the river and what comes next is the
mountain and I say wow how this
raft was very useful to me I'm going to carry it
to climb the mountain but guess
what carrying a heavy
wooden raft while you're climbing a mountain
is not the best idea but you don't let go
because that raft saved your life at one
point but it's no longer helping you
climb the mountain you can no longer continue
climbing you have to let go of that
raft you can be grateful for what it gave you
but the  you have to leave it on the
riverbank because now what you need are
other tools to climb the
mountain our attachment styles
sometimes we drag them through
the most diverse and
unfortunate scenarios when they no longer
work for us yes it's true that it worked for me to pretend
that nothing hurt to
avoid them continuing to hurt me but
Ho it doesn't work for me anymore no longer I can't
carry that behavior into the future even if it's what
my mind tells me that's what you have to
do if someone makes you
angry don't talk to them silent treatment that's how
things get solved it's like when they
ask you are angry or upset
Hey what's wrong and what do they usually
answer until a chorus and we didn't
agree exactly and I say why do we
answer nothing instead of saying you know
what if I'm angry because you promised to
call me and you didn't call me if I feel
upset because you didn't keep your
word on what you told me you were going to
do but we say nothing because
one says why should I tell them if nothing is going to
change So that impulse to answer
nothing we should recognize it and
then say let's see  There I go again to
say nothing There I go again to stamp my feet
when I'm angry without speaking There I go
again to slam the door There I go
again to leave it on seen on the phone
so that he learns that
these things are not done to me and there I'm going to have him in the
freezer until he learns his lesson
Why not better to say let's see it's the
strangest thing a patient told me the other
day I always insisted for a long
time why don't you talk to your mom
why don't you talk to your mom why don't you
talk to your mom and her response was no no no you ca
n't talk to my mom my
mom doesn't listen my mom is like this
my mom is like that and she
stops talking one day I think that
before desperation she writes to me and says
Mario what do you think I did what I talked to
my mom and I say What happened this is
magic because things started to
resolve between us First she
listened to me and I also realized that I was
n't listening to her either so
doing something so
counterintuitive like instead of
saying nothing when you do have something because
you see that you have something is to say  yes I am
angry I am upset I am sad I
feel frustrated And that is the first step
to recognizing and changing these
patterns If we are not going to be condemned
to repetition because we are going to give in to
these old paths that are the
known paths now it is not that we
are stupid we are activating
defense mechanisms that were very
useful in the past but the point is
that we continue carrying carrying rafts
when we are climbing mountains and we are
carrying ice axes and harnesses when we are
crossing the river each tool is useful
for something each tool
provides us with something but you have to know how to
use it you have to know how to apply it in the
appropriate context So if we always
carry a hammer in our hand it can
be very useful Not when you see a
loose nail it's done but suddenly you have a
hammer in your hand and you see a baby
suddenly you have one in your hand and you see a
very tasty dessert suddenly you have a
hammer in your hand and you are next to the
person that you like so much but you don't
let go of the hammer and let's see if I'll give you
a caress Well I'm not going to eat my
dessert No well I'm not going to break an egg well
no and it does not mean that
hammers are not useful it's where and
how I'm using it Those are the
attachment styles how I'm going to use
this that I know is in humans this
way of bonding but you
will tell me Hey Mario but if I get close to
someone and they give me the cold shoulder if I get close to
someone and they betray me Ah the person with
secure attachment what do you think they also know how to do set
limits if I get close and you
betray me if I get close you lie to me if I get
close and you hurt me I will tell you Hey no like that No like that
because that hurts me Ay Ay how it's
going to hurt you if you come from a cactus mom
yes I come from there but I'm not condemned
to live in a territory of pure
succulent not where I'm all thorny
all the time no no fair because
Where I come from is what I don't want anymore like that no no
enough and up to here these are words that
a person with secure attachment uses I don't
use them not from anxious attachment because they say no
if I say no they won't love me anymore
better I better endure better I endure Because
in the end it doesn't hurt me so much I had a
patient  that she told me how her boyfriend
insulted her, he minimized her and every time she
told me about one of these episodes she always
ended by saying but Mario Nothing's happening
and Mario Nothing's happening and and and one day I
told her Ending a session you know what I would
like something to happen in your life
because nothing ever happens You know what I would
like to happen that one day you would say
enough no up to here I can no longer
continue allowing this treatment why
because I love myself because I know that I am a
valuable person And because you know that you are
a valuable person because I am me look at
a nursery selection from a nursery What is
the valuable baby And the baby that is not
worth it let me explain then We wouldn't have
Why question our value we are
people we are sentient beings
we are living beings we all deserve to be
loved we all deserve to be loved And the
one who approaches us to
hurt us
not like that no not like that thank you very much but
this This is not for me that is
secure attachment in action thanks for
asking hello Mario how are you I am Daniel
montesdeoca I really appreciate the
talk I think it helps us a lot to get
to know ourselves and know why  we decided
what we decided my question would be how does
attachment influence our
work decisions imagine a
person who is constantly
anxious thinking if they are doing
things right at work if their
boss is okay with it if what I
'm doing will be enough if I should be
giving more spending all my
time comparing myself to others it's not
that he stayed longer I should
stay longer it's not that he also
works Saturdays and Sundays I should
work Saturdays and Sundays I shouldn't
be resting I should be
producing these are the people who
then feel a lot of guilt when they are
on a day off when they think they should be getting
ahead on the
work because what is the boss going to say
how are my colleagues going to see me
remember for example with the
anxious attachment style there is a lot of this search for
external validation And then you can
project onto a boss a superior the
figure of a father or a mother to whom I
feel that I have to please or maybe
not sometimes worse sometimes I become
conflictive at work these are the
people that suddenly you don't know how to
approach them because of  suddenly they are
very cooperative suddenly they do not talk to you
suddenly they react with certain
aggressiveness and violence and you know what they
say out there sometimes they hire us
for what we know and fire us For
who we are or the way we are
So an attachment style can
determine the way we relate for
example a person with habitatio attachment has a
hard time making a team and
working as a team and we see this from
school people who say oh no
teamwork no what the hell I better
do everything I do it's that the others do not
work I do everything better alone not
when your mom tells you Hey why wasn't it
teamwork Yes yes yes but I
do it alone because I do it better and
I want to get a good grade
so you do everything and the others Well
the other one is going to be everything No why
Because you do not know how to work as a team
because you can no longer trust others
because you think that others are
necessarily going to do it wrong because you
think that you have to do everything That it is
better alone than in bad company and
that type of things it is hard to
make friends at work or
you make friends with practically
anyone and you trust  too soon or you do
n't trust So imagine these
links in our work performance
how they influence our relationships
as well, for example I think that this
phrase I didn't come to work to be
friends was invented by one of
avoidant attachment because there because
work also makes friends No, that's it I did
n't come here to be liked we are all
social beings, I mean yes it matters the
avoidant attachment would say I don't
care if they like me or dislike me
for example a bad leader calling
a person who doesn't manage
their emotions well a bad leader curiously is the one who
could say I don't care if I
'm popular here you have to do what
I say Oh By the way, that's what a
father said to a mother I don't care that you
love me As long as you are afraid of me it is
enough then creating, forming,
leading or working under these schemes
becomes something that not only perpetuates
these states but can through
emotional co-regulation infect
other people with this and can also
in some way affect our
work performance because finally we are
going to think that I do everything well as
expected my satisfaction is not full I am
always going to think that  something remains to be
seen I will always think that I could have done
better I will always think
that one day they will discover that I am a
fraud that I am not as much as they think not this
famous imposter syndrome and all the
things that derive from it but but the
root of all this even of our
self-esteem has to do with our
attachment styles because if those
examples sound familiar to you suddenly Hey this seems like a
person with low self-esteem a person
who wants to be accommodating all the
time yes yes it sounds familiar That is so
because ultimately there is the base let's
think that these attachment styles are
like the script and our life is like a
theater and this is the stage where
we play yes We will always be
playing our roles in these
scripts we would have to ask ourselves well what
character am I What character was assigned to me am I
the Eternally Accommodating am I the
loner who solves everything by
himself am I the unstable one it could not be the
character of the crazy one no that you never know
how he will react or am I the person
who can say let's see there are roles that I do
not want to play and it is true
that I remember that a patient told me that she
had a boss a leader of her
team that was a person, according to what she
told me, very explosive and very
irascible, but my patient was very
vulnerable. I believe that there was a combination of a
disorganized attachment style with an
anxious attachment style and she always
wanted to please her but she couldn't
please her and since she couldn't please her,
that boss always yelled at her and
scolded her and there came a day when this
lady, this leader, told her when she starts it's
not possible that she doesn't get to me.  Let's be honest, I've
told you many
times, and my patient starts to cry and
she says, Oh, you're going to get
emotional, and she tells me in the session, he says,
Mario, he told me that, I tell her. You
can always respond and you too. I get
emotional towards anguish and you get
emotional towards anger because anger
is also an emotion. Both were
emotional, but how curious is that we
recognize an emotional person
only when they cry. Oh, you're very emotional.
An angry person is an
emotional person. A happy person. They are an
emotional person. A curious person is an
emotional person. Emotions move us
and so we have to recognize every
emotion as a part of
our human experience. I know that they have
told us that there are positive and
negative emotions, and it's true, but negative ones
are not bad like positive ones, they are not
good. Just like the raft, just like the
hammer, everything is useful in some context,
and where it applies to sadness,
sadness is welcomed, where it applies to
joy, joy is welcomed,
and where it applies to anger, to
set limits, it is said, eh. No, no, no, no.  I
like it when you talk to me this way
I don't like it when you yell at me but when
you're really afraid that if you lose
this job you'll never
get another one like you're really afraid that
everyone will criticize you and see you as
a conflictive person better as they say if I
keep quiet I look prettier Because this way I do
n't make waves but I keep swallowing it I keep holding on I keep
holding on these thorns
of this cactus and I'm suffering
so we stay in jobs that are little or
less convenient for us
sometimes we stay in places that don't
correspond with what we want they don't
transport us to our to
our better future to our dreams I'm
going to say it like this that can happen to us
with an attachment style that is not an
adequate attachment style We tolerate it
or we jump from job to job
no no we don't find satisfaction you change jobs
six times a year and one will say you
're exploring Yes but you're 57
years old it's like the exploration lasted a
little beyond what it should have No
because you haven't achieved stability and
then Yes we go to
relationships too where you also say u the
same thing happens to me It's not  that this is a
mirror this stage is the same nothing
else changes the scenery you can put
a scenery of an office the
scenery of a family any
scenery you want in the end the
problem is the scripts that we have
learned to read and that we are following that is why we
are repeating patterns it does not
matter if they put Aldal Lama here and
here we can have Gandhi it does not matter
we are going to cause conflict if we do not
have a healthy attachment style
hello Mario I have some questions about
how parents can heal their wounds
so as not to transmit them to their children and
also a little how as children we can
understand this process thank you for the
question it is complicated because
wanting another person to
change implies that the other person
first wants to change but to want to
change you have to realize that something has to be
changed why do I tell you all this
because for me the word the concept is
humility the humility that combats
arrogance that combats pride and
combats this idea that since I am your father I
am your mother I know everything and you
cannot question me absolutely You are welcome whether
you are a small child or a
50 year old person I am your  father I am
your mother and I am
unquestionable it seems that the
moment we have a child that
having a child is different from being parents
because being parents is more active having a
child is a biological fact but being
parents is a whole process but but it happens
that suddenly It seems that we
become omniscient beings at the
birth of a child no I mean I am
Mario Guerra here without a child my
first child is born the next second I already
became someone unquestionable and
a kind of God no humility the
humility of saying it is true I also
learned things I learned many
things from my father many things from my
father And many things from my mother that
have served me a lot throughout my
life but I also have to recognize
that I learned many things from them that
are footprints that I do not want to follow that I do
not want to follow because they are not
good for me Because they were from another time, another
era or a different reality or
Because they were on a different path than
mine and I am grateful for everything they
taught me but I say this I will keep
and this I will not keep but I will never  to be
able to see that if I don't have this humility
to ask myself what I'm doing
we should approach the children and
ask them no no like I said a
moment ago when we do this
inventory to see what you lacked House
food toys school sports you had
everything It's not to ask what you feel
you lacked what you would like me to have done
differently what you would like me to
do differently now mom dad I would
like you not to criticize my decisions
mom dad I would like you to
know feel that I have a little support but of course if the answer is good but how am I going to give you my support is pure nonsense no Okay then we're going backwards again no how do you need my support how do you need it what do you need from me sometimes we think that we have to give
the big lesson not the big speech to our
children young or old
and it has happened to me that sometimes with a
hug things are resolved much
better but it's not because it's the hug
therapy so talked about out there but
because a hug transmits this This
acceptance this
How can I not love you How can I not
love you despite your anger
despite you coming and going and and and how can I
not love you  things that you do that
I don't like clearly there are things that I would
like you to do in a
different way But I know that I can't take
that path because it is Your path and I know that you are
going to take a lot of things but
then it would be this humility and this
approach Look
Hey my new book is out it's
called Leave Me Alone Mom and You Too
Dad one says clear I'm going to buy it
to set limits with my mother and
right now she's going to listen to me Leave me
alone mom it's not Shut up and don't
talk leave me alone it's not her it's not
him it's Those internal voices that we have that
keep on praying in our heads not
when one is saying right now I'm going to do
but I'm doing wrong of course what would
my mother tell me in this case think
about many of the things that you do what would my mother tell me
if she knew what I
was doing she would tell me that it's not done she would tell me that it's not done like that she would
say that it's
better this way she would give me her way
of seeing the world So I believe that
always the most loving approach of
saying to you dad mom I would like you to
meet me today because you met the one that I was Of course
Yes, you even have pictures there,
pictures of me at the fair, pictures
of my birthday, but you know what? I'm
the age I am now and I think I've changed,
and I think you've changed too, and I would
like for us to get to know each other, to
recognize each other, to give each other the
chance to get to know each other again, who we are
today, but that only happens through
conversations, through
this non-violent, non-
threatening approach. Oh, since I've already gone to therapy,
the therapist told me that you are the
cause of all my misfortunes and now you
have to
listen to me, well, who wants to hear that?
Frankly,
not once with my own mother, my mom is
still alive,
eh. She doesn't remember us anymore because she
sees us and asks us what our names are, she's
years old and that's it.
But one day, as an adult, we would
visit her on weekends and go to her
parents' house, and one day, while we were at
the table, my mom, like any other day,
was scolding us all, you this,
you that, you the other, and I approached her and
said, mom, I don't like it when you
scold me, I really like coming to see
you and I really like being with you,
but you  You scold me a lot for things that I do
n't understand why If there's something that you
would like me to change Tell me but I'm going to
ask you not to scold me Because if you
scold me so much I'm going to keep
coming but I'm not going to feel good And I
don't want to not feel good when I'm
with you I'm going to ask you please not to
do it There was silence at the table
all my brothers turning to look at
my mom turning to look at me I said here There's
going to be a mess my mom
looked at me and said yes it's okay And from
that day on she never scolded me again she
's a brother
Yes that's not humility the
loving limits and I have to recognize my
mother's humility that she had at that
moment just as I have to recognize my father's
humility as I
also have to review my own
humility because I can't be the
omniscient father who knows everything who is never
wrong Although it's fun sometimes to
put yourself in this role but no no it's
also learning but being willing
when you're not willing costs a lot
more work  and that's when one has to
take distance so as to not continue
hurting and not continue hurting ourselves
Thank you for
[Applause]
[Music]
questions Uh My question is can
I take advantage of attachment
direct it towards something
positive thank you Yes of course because we
are going to have attachment the question is how are we
going to direct it precisely how are we
going to direct it towards a space that
is more useful to us that is more
benevolent more beneficial for
us and our world of relationships
yes fortunately yes it is possible to
change it although it is true that the
attachment style is formed in childhood
in the first years of our life
through upbringing with our parents it
is not a condemnation it is not an
indelible tattoo and even tattoos
can now be erased It's not true then
Then yes it is possible but we require
several elements the first is to be
aware that something something is not something is not
as I want it to be with me
something is happening and that happens by finding
patterns Let's see why do I always come across
people who betray me Why do I
always come across cold and
distant people why do I always come across  with
people I run into people who abuse
me and one begins to think it will be bad
luck or who is the common denominator
in all those relationships will it be me and that
is the first step first to recognize what
should improve so that
this begins to change then
obviously comes the will and the
commitment What do I have to do sometimes
the help and accompaniment of a
therapist can be the best idea but
sometimes even model observing others
suddenly you say let's see Why is it that my
partners always say that I am
very manipulative and very controlling let's see I'm
going to observe myself Of course because after 5
minutes that he doesn't answer me Where are you
What are you doing Let's see send me a
photo proof of life with who not And
then I realize that the people
who are with me my friends tell you
Hey and your girlfriend and I well she's at home
but no she's not going to write to him or no pu I already
wrote to him a while ago but what if he left well he left But
where did he go and you
well I don't know you say what a strange person
no but he starts to look at others
who suddenly do the same thing and you say
Ah  gee, is there another way to
relate other than always
asking for proof, asking for reinforcement,
asking for constant validation, the
people we surround ourselves with becomes very
important and it's something that is hardly
talked about because we always seek this
process, therapy for me, go to
therapy, it's that we are really good at
sending people to therapy, go to
therapy, you are really bad, not telling
the mirror, this would be interesting, but,
in addition, we have to understand that in
a social context, in a
cultural context, other people also
influence. Of course, if you are going to surround yourself with
people who are suddenly as
manipulative, controlling, or kind of
paranoid as oneself, no, if you touch
someone from, Hey, what are you doing? No,
writing to my boyfriend to see where he
is. Yes, me too, to mine, yes, let's see what, what
are you telling him? Well,
send me a photo, you're right, send me a photo, well,
that doesn't help, no, because they are people
who are feeding
and something happens here that I use the word
macabre with the matter, a person with a
secure attachment is not going to tend to
relate to a person with an
anxious, avoidant, or disorganized attachment.
Securely attached person feels more
confident with a securely attached person
And so what does that mean? Well, that
then people with anxious,
avoidant, and disorganized attachment are going to
relate to each other and they are going to
feed off each other because the
securely attached person says I don't
understand this, I don't know why you're
asking me this, why is the other person asking me, I I I I
better go, he knows how to set limits
so we would have to look for ourselves, procure for ourselves
not only the necessary reflection, what
we are doing, this
self-knowledge of being able to identify
with something that we are
talking about here, but also be
willing to look to change something in
ourselves, whether it's asking for help. The
securely attached person can also
ask for help without any problem. It's not the one who
says, I've had patients who
suddenly get the phone in therapy.
Mario. This is going to answer, I answer.
Okay, they answer. Yes, well, Yes, I'm in
a meeting. Yes, I'll call you later. Oh, sorry,
Mario. It's that I don't want, I don't want them to
know that I'm coming with the shrink, no, and I'm
like this, thank you, um, no, and people who say,
Yes, I'm in my therapy. I'll call you right
now, no, and  hang up the call
Okay, okay, from there, no, where I don't have to be
hiding as if it were a
defect, we have to understand something, the
way you have of relating,
your relationship pattern is not a
personality defect, it is a style that you
had to develop to survive
in the environment that you survived
emotionally and that now is no longer
useful in many
contexts we have to grow, I no
longer wear the sailor suit that
I wore when I was 3 years old because it no longer fits me, I
no longer carry it when I
go to the mountains because it is no longer
helpful to me, I have to dress in a
different way, I have to carry
different tools that can make my
life easier and be willing to do that, but
also very
important are the people we
surround ourselves with, the people we hang out with, I
sometimes say there are friends that we
may love
very much but we shouldn't follow their
example and we may believe them too much and we cannot
make them change either, but
when one realizes that one can
be an engine of change, not only for
oneself but one without meaning to, in these
co-regulation skills, being able to
tell an
anguished person, calm down, they will surely
answer your message right now, you just sent them
send message a minute ago you don't
know what you're doing sometimes I
tell people when they touch me
anxious people on the other side of the
message Mario I sent you a message I tell you it's that
you don't know what I'm doing
on this side you don't know if I'm
bathing If I'm eating if I'm with
a child if I am you don't know what I'm
doing on this side you think that one
would be on the other side already like a
bush assault to see what time a message comes in
to see what time a message comes in it's not like that
at least I have to take out the phone to
answer it so start
doing this this modeling of regulation
in society also helps we are
people who sometimes look at the root of the
pandemic anxiety worldwide
rose by 20 percent and has not returned to
pre-pandemic levels and we don't know if it will
return but anxiety does not come from the
air it is us who with
anxious behaviors can
suddenly infect others in
this So this regulation
allows us to self-regulate and
regulate them and that is one of the great
things we can do in addition to seeking
help when needed that is always
important because there are people who  They say
no, how embarrassing I should already be because it
's another form of organized attachment You
should solve your problems by
yourself you shouldn't have to ask
anyone fast what the therapist is going to see
They surely have worse
problems than you don't And surely we do
too on average 70
percent of people drop out of therapy
in the third session and they drop out
because they feel like they're not changing and
I tell them And how are you going to feel like you
're changing with three sessions this
is a process there are going to be relapses of
course there are going to be relapses it would be
ideal if we could say let's see I've already
identified that I have an anxious attachment style I've
already identified that I have an
avoidant attachment style all right the
world stop please I'm going to fix my
attachment style nobody move everything
stay as it is I'm going to fix my
attachment style and when I fix it I'll take it off
pause and we'll get back to life it's not
possible and it's not necessary out there I've
heard people who say We
shouldn't have relationships with anyone or
have children until we have a
style  of healthy attachment No, well we
would have already become
extinct there are no things we have to
do along the way there are things we have to
do along the way and we are going to
relapse But it is not the same to go back
again slamming the door when I am
angry and creating a conflict with the
person who lives in my house than to go back
slamming the door and coming back and saying
sorry again I let go of the door
because I am angry We had already talked about that
this is something I do not want to do
but we have also talked about how it is
costing me but I want to ask you for forgiveness
again for having done
this but this helps me remember that it
is not something that I want to do that is the
big difference this awareness
and this recognition yes you are going to
fall again clearly you are going to fall again
how we learned the fundamentals of
life how you learned to walk Little by
little you got up walking like this
mother How are you Look how we learned to
speak
and not we learned to speak one day out of
nowhere and we say mother I want to recite
a poem that I just assimilated How
we learned to eat making a mess with trial and
error everything is  trial and error well
learning a different attachment style is
as important and as complex as
learning to eat for yourself as
learning to walk as learning something
fundamental for life
we are going to fall into old patterns but
those those old patterns are not
bad news they are the reminder that
we are moving forward they are the reminder that
we are on the right path Mario But
how will the reminder of that be? Of
course because before it happened to you that I slammed
the door and you didn't realize and I didn't
even apologize today you
realize that makes you feel bad you go back to
apologize and that reinforces your
desire I need to modify this I need to
trust more I need to take breaks I
need to take some space that but we are
going to relapse we are going to relapse because
remember this is like a furrow we are not going to have to get
out of the furrow but we are going to
fall again but perseverance and
here there is a word as I said with the
parents that is needed as parents
humility to recognize that there are things
that we have taught that are nothing more
fortunate And in this case the word is
perseverance perseverance is
different from stubbornness for which
Stubbornness is wanting to do the same thing over and
over and over again, wanting
different results. Perseverance
is doing one thing and if that doesn't work,
doing something else. And if that doesn't work, doing something
else. Until you get the result you
want. I had an
American teacher who told me, "I
once went to learn how to ski." He
told me, "I went to Aspen and  I wanted to ski
and I arrived and I was very excited because
the first day that I arrived I didn't know how to
ski and I saw how not even children,
older people, men, women were launching themselves down this
Loma with their skis and I said no that's it
and I hired the best
ski instructor I arrived to that class and he said
very well Put on your skis I put on my
skis let's see fasten them very well
Now unfasten your skis and the other
Okay I unfastened my skis fasten them again fasten
the skis unfasten them again
and that was the whole
choice of the day and he said listen but I
want to ski that's why This is the
first choice Okay and and and the instructor He
told me surely tomorrow I would
learn to ski I arrived okay fasten my
skis very well Now take the
poles adjust the poles very well Take
off the poles Take off the skis put
the skis back on
put the poles back on My instructor already told me I
said  this guy is ripping me off
everyone I see them launching themselves down
the mountain skiing first
class and this one the skis and the poles
third class something similar fourth class
is put on your skis put on your poles
adjust now throw yourself on the ground How Throw yourself Throw yourself on the
ground like this sideways fall
Yeah now get up now Take off your
skis now Take off your poles and he
said you know what you're ripping me off
because I want to learn to ski
Exactly that's why you're here tomorrow you're going to be
able to finally launch yourself down the Hill I
arrived the next day he told me and I
understood I understood what was happening
because when I launched myself I realized that
everyone who had launched themselves in the
first session without learning anything else
were lying down with a ski over there the
pole over there upside down everything
was chaos and I was able to get down And yes I fell
but my skis didn't come off because
I had tightened them well and
one pole came loose but I was able to put it on again by
myself and I was able to reach the end which
almost nobody could do sometimes we want to
result without going through the process
but falling implies the most important thing
How to know how to get up and culturally
we are taught that we shouldn't fall
that we shouldn't go back or to
gain momentum as they say but I say
then how do we learn tell tell tell
that to a child there is no such phrase that
says if you're not going to do things right
better not do them I say Who invented that
say that to a child who is
learning to walk Ah no if you're not going to
learn to walk well better
never walk Say that to a child who is
learning to speak Ah if you're not going to
learn to speak well Better never
speak Better never eat by yourself we would never
return we would become
parasitic beings no we don't do that why do we
do it to ourselves why do we
expect immediate results from ourselves
Well because of our attachment style Of course I'm
already feeling stupid I feel like
I'm not Progressing I feel like others are
doing better I feel like everyone
is doing well And not me because s Of course
my mother was right I am stubborn I am a
fool I have a head of stone I am an ass
and those voices start again and there
we remember the Leave me alone mom and you
too Dad are Those internal voices that
stay with us So yes know
that everything important in this life
is learned through a process of
trial and error and that is how
perfection is achieved That is how we come out on the other
side when it is not that we avoid falling
if when we learn to get up
That is the way thanks for
[Applause]
asking hello Mario My name is Amanda
nice to meet you Uh my question is focused on
daily life eh all access to
social networks to the media Do you think that
the form of attachment has changed
Look I remember for Celso a
Swiss doctor from the Middle Ages who said everything is
poison nothing is poison it all depends on the
dose I do not believe that
social networks and the media
have come to cause us anxiety if
not the way we use them has
been a vehicle to be able to be close
in this distant communication through
instant messaging and
that strengthens a bond of attachment but they have also
served as a vehicle for people who
unleash their anxiety there in this
immediacy of the networks in this
suddenly  observe and decontextualize a
post why did you like
that person because where were you because you
were happier in this photo I have
had people who suddenly on their
wall of their social networks have
photos that are there at a
birthday with a previous partner for
example no And then suddenly it is not that
why were you happier with him there why are you
not so happy with me
because there it is seen that you were
enjoying it with me he is suffering
right of course So they have become
a vehicle to give free rein
to our anxieties in our
disorganized ways But it is the way
we use them it is true you said you put your finger
on the sore something very
important how is it possible that in the
pandemic we have been in
confinement dying to go
out to hug to celebrate to be with
our loved ones And suddenly it seems that we have
forgotten that we realize for
example that today many people already have a
hard time expressing non-
verbal emotions with their face for example
because they are children who have been raised in
generations where there was not much of this There was
not anymore because now the sight and
the face is on the cell phone they are
no longer here So now it is Look mom
this dinosaur Oh how pretty it turned
out Look dad what I'm doing Oh How fun no Then this part of now is gone you drew a blue dinosaur How cool it turned out no And this child's face like this Yes, that's true I did it No this gesticulation we have been losing a lot of this in these generations
precisely because we are very immersed
as we have been told that we are multitasking
and the reality is that yes we can do
two things at once but the quality of
those interactions decreases a lot
when it comes to being with someone
particularly with any person
but with any small child We
should not be in their presence unless it is
truly imperative to be
constantly on the cell phone
I know that r are fun
but it shouldn't be more fun what your
child is doing no It should be more
fun Oh the sound of the
cars is not as funny as this just
look at the cat in the hat
What a wonderful thing you have a
hat and it is a cat no then
go away then it seems that the cat in the
hat is more fun and yes it may be
but we have a
responsibility also what am I
transmitting What message am I sending
So they are not those networks I
should not be able to self-regulate too
How many times have you not wanted to talk to
someone and you tell them something Hey I want to
tell you something and the person is on their
cell phone and until the
moment comes you know what? Better forget it I do
n't feel like telling you but why
if I'm paying attention to you yes you have to pay attention
But there you have to make it
seem like you pay attention too not
only do it so that the other person
notices That's why I said before it is as important to
love as to know how to love and knowing how to love is
knowing how to transmit the love you feel for the
other person in a way that the other person receives it
as love This is how
a
healthy attachment style is based on knowing that for the other I
am important knowing that in this moment
that we are in interaction there is nothing
more important than us I understand that
after I go to school you go to
work and other things become
important but at the moment of our
interaction what we should
prioritize is precisely that this
interaction between us after I
go to the bathroom and there before I carried a
newspaper I don't take my cell phone now
there and and there they can  find out about many
things but but not when we are with
another person not when we are
interacting with friends not when we are
interacting with
children because the networks are not poisonous it
is the dose that is what makes a
fundamental difference and that is what
can be the difference between a
secure attachment style of a boy who
comes to think a girl who comes to
think I am important I am more
important than the cat in the hat
That is what I want to convey to the
little ones that there is nothing more important
at this moment
than you and I being together Thank you for
asking and the other one also
human contact for me everything has
changed is not this anymore because of the age that I
have
this I think that the couple the family the
friends Human contact has been lost let's
see you have to understand something not because
because here we are today in Mexico we
are in Mexico and you see how they say
that Mexicans Mexicans are
very attached and we are very family oriented there is
a cultural element in all of this
Remember that we learn everything from three
fundamental sources family society and
culture so in the cultural framework
where we are there are no cultures where
children leave home at 16 years old
the university to study not the United States
an example of them and and they
separate very soon from the family niche in
that culture that is what is seen that is what is
promoted And that is what
happens in a normal way in our
cultural environment It is true that we are
more attached to the family on Sundays
at grandma's house not when sometimes
one says I don't want to go to grandma's house anymore
But when they tell you
how many years is your grandma going to live you
should go because then the day that you are going to be
No there comes our
emotional blackmail and one does not yes I have to
see my grandma and then we go to
grandma's every weekend to
be close to be with family and one has a
good time but one says Well how do I know
that these dynamics of being so attached
to the family are not dynamics that are the product
of an anxious attachment style that
leads me to be here just in fear it is
very easy these dynamics that are a
product of our culture one
enjoys them one enjoys them and one is
fine there and and one can say one day
look today I am not coming  to grandma's house
because I have a get-together with my friends
and it's no big deal more than to say man we
're going to miss you and you yes I know but
but next week I'm going perfect no
problem the problem is how come you're
not going to come I hope I hope that the
next time you come you'll still
find me because no I haven't felt
well then when the
blackmail starts when the criticism starts
how can it be that you're like that bad son you
want to go to a party When your poor
mother is here subjugated in the kitchen
cooking for you and you want to leave
that there how is it possible that you won't eat
her chile nogada that she prepared for you with so much love
and you but I don't
like chiles enogada well you
have to eat it to please your
mother who prepared it for you with so much love
mom I've already told you not to make chiles
enogada well I made it for you with so much love and
you're going to eat it ungrateful no
then there's someone who eats chile noada
that he doesn't even like it half arching the
matter not because it's bad it must be
very good but I don't like it no
Angry chiles but if they force me to
eat them Well then there is a
problem because then they are
conditioning me because then this
disorganized attachment style comes where bad
yes yes bad if not if I eat it I vomit
and if I don't eat it I am already a bad son
so I have to choose between
my indigestion and my and my bad
condition as a son to be able to be
happy in this family so that's when we
realize Beyond the cultural that
we are family we are close in
general Latinos are like that when
these conditionings come these
veiled and not so veiled threats of
you have to be here because you can't
miss Well it just happened to me
recently with a patient who
suddenly uh the mother of a
friend dies And so it was She was a very
close relative of that family of my patient
so a member of the family of my
patient can't go to the mass because he
is traveling and then they tell him how are you
not going to go to Juanita's mass
Well the thing is that I am in another place that
unconscious You knew that the mass was
today but I had to work no sooner
later you see that there was no affection How well you
know  Friends are known in
jail and in the hospital, they have told us that
many times and I say No, well I
have met my friends at parties,
frankly no, yes, and I have had friends, very
good friends who do not like to go to the
hospital for some personal reason and they are
still my friends. I have
people that I see every day and they are not
really my friends and people that I hardly
see and they are my best friends. My best
friend Ivan lives in the Canary Islands. He
is from the Canary Islands and I met him
studying when I went to the
Canary Islands to do a master's degree in thanatology
and he became my best friend and he lives on the other
side of the world. We do not see each other that often.
But we are best friends despite that.
Because those are the links because the
link, as I said, is like an
emotional bond that forms between two
people and that bond can stretch
to the other side of the world. Or it might not
form. Even being with the person who
is with you, even seeing them every
day. If it is a person, for example, who
avoids, if it is a person who rejects, if it
is a person who is very afraid of
forming bonds, it is not the distance, it is not
the frequency, it is the quality of the link.
will determine the quality of
our relationships yes we are family
we are attached there is nothing wrong with that
as long as that attachment does not turn into
fear conditioning or threats
of abandonment or not belonging that
is also true Mario it is a pleasure to meet you and I
want to ask you how to become
self-sufficient and happy very well thank you very much thank you
for your
question self-sufficient and happy I believe
that happiness is a process not a
destination I have always thought
so if we think about emotional self-sufficiency we
would have to think of something
if we get the idea that being
emotionally self-sufficient means that
I do not need anyone and that I can handle
all of that alone it is called
avoidant attachment self-sufficiency implies being
able to be surrounded by
people but not depending entirely
on any of
them enjoying their presence knowing
that that presence can be transitory
in our lives like grandparents
parents sometimes even friends
but also knowing that
we are there and that we too can
at any given moment seek help support
from others and also seek the
darkest in the most
difficult moments we can always even
turn to our ancestors
symbolically invoke them as me
A patient said, I wish a
higher power would come and take care of me and I told him,
look, I don't know if a higher power exists,
but it seems that the
higher power needs you to learn to take
care of yourself so that it can take care of you,
you need to be the instrument for
it, so I think that
we could be self-sufficient,
sharing, being self-sufficient and
happy knowing that we are, the time
that we are, that we enjoy each other, that we
also have differences but we
fix them, that we have problems but we
clarify them, that we talk, that we converse, that we
give each other and that we
also accept each other's apologies,
I met a person who said, Well,
Mario, it's very easy for someone to ask for forgiveness
and now, what else can he
do? If he stepped on you, he ca
n't unsee you, so yes,
obviously he asks for forgiveness and changes his
behavior, he'll be more careful next
time, but we should
also be receptive to that, to
realize that there are people who love us
very much and who can also
hurt us, and also the fact that we are
interdependent does not make us more
vulnerable, on the contrary, it makes us
stronger, it makes us stronger to have more
people to lean on, and that doesn't make
us  It takes away self-sufficiency or takes away our
independence. So we have to
understand this. I said it at the beginning and I say it
now. We do not have to opt for
detachment. That is not possible nor is it
healthy. The bond of attachment is
something natural that is given from
birth, the search for love,
protection, and care, and we will
continue to need it our entire lives, but
eventually, when we become
adults, our primary source is
self-reliance. We are going to make our
primary source of love, care, and
closeness, and attachment, but we will do it
through others because we heal through
our bonds, we heal through
our relationships. I do not ask someone to
heal me, but I am
healing. But it is not the healing of an
illness, it is the healing of
heartbreak, it is being able to provide ourselves with
loving environments, warm environments, close environments
where I feel welcome and where I also feel
welcome. And it does not
matter that today you identify
with the worst, the most terrible
attachment style that may have
existed on the face of the
earth, that is not a condemnation. If you
decide first to recognize that you need to
change, then seek help.
necessary to do it They commit
to the perseverance of change and
surround themselves with people who are more
similar to the actors and characters they
want to have on the stage of their lives
only in this way will we rewrite
new ones We are grateful for what we were taught
We take what is good and does us good
and let go of what does not allow us to
grow This is a great opportunity for
all of us to
identify How what we were
taught was a vision of the world but
today we can develop a
different vision a vision of more
Hope a vision of more love a
vision where not only me but
everyone around me is welcome
around me Thank you for listening to me thank you
all for being here
[Applause]
[Music]